<?xml-model href="tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>

<TEI xml:id="basicTEI.478-878" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>

                <title level="a" type="main">Lynching from a Negro's Point of View</title>
            </titleStmt>

            <editionStmt>
                <edition>
                    <date>2021</date>
                </edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>University of Nebraska- Lincoln </publisher>

                <date>2021</date>

            </publicationStmt>

            <notesStmt>
                <note type="project"/>
            </notesStmt>

            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl>
                    <title level="a"/>
                    <editor/>
                    <author/>
                    <date when="1904" notBefore="1904" notAfter="1904"/>
                    <publisher/>
                    <pubPlace><!-- place of publication --></pubPlace>
                    <orgName> </orgName>
                </bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <p/>
            </editorialDecl>
        </encodingDesc>

        <revisionDesc>
            <change when="20210302"> <name>Jessie McCloy</name> Transcribed and Encoded
                Excerpt</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>

    <text>
        <front>
            <head>Introduction</head>
            <p>Mary Church Terrell was an upper class African American woman who used her position
                to fight for racial equality and women's suffrage. Born in 1863, Both her her father
                and mother were successful business owners. Her father was even one of the South's
                first African American millionaries. </p>
            <p>Terrell owned both a Bachelor's and a Master's degree at Oberlin College, a school
                that admitted both African Americans and women, and began a career teaching high
                schoolers. It is at M Street Colored High School where she met and married her
                husband and had one daughter and one adoptive daughter.</p>
            <p>Terrell's activism began with the death of an old friend, Thomas Moss, in 1892. He
                was lynched by a mob due to the fact that he owned a competing business. This caused
                her to speak out against lynching, such as she did in this speech. She both helped
                found and became the president of the NACW, the National Association of Colored
                Women.</p>
            <p>Terrell was an important activist in her time and she was and still is an great role
                model in the fight for justice and equality. Today, many people probably find it
                hard to believe that public murder happened and that the murders, large groups of
                people, were able to walk away without justice being served. Yet, this was common
                and a real dillemma for people like Terrell, who were the targets of this racial
                hate crime. Terrell did not stand idly by as this stuff happened, and neither should
                anyone in the face of injustice, that is why Terrell's work and this speech is still
                important to this day. </p>
        </front>
        <body>
            <div>
                <pb n="2" facs="Terrell_Image2.png"/>
                <head>Lynching From A Negro's Point of View</head>
                <head>By Mary Church Terrell, Honorary President of the National Association of
                    Colored Women </head>
                <p>Before 1904 was three months old, thirty-one negroes had been lynched. Of this
                    number, <ref target="#Arkansas_Lynching"> fifteen were murdered within one week
                    in Arkansas,</ref> and one was shot to death in Springfield, Ohio, by a mob
                    composed of men who did not take the trouble to wear masks. Hanging, shooting,
                    and burning black men, women, and children in the United States have become so
                    common that such occurrences create but little sensation and evoke but alight
                    comment now. Those who are jealous of their country's fair name feel keenly the
                    necessity of extripating this lawlessness, which is
                    <choice><sic>no</sic><corr>now</corr></choice> widespread and has taken such
                    deep root. But means of prevention can never be devised, until the cause of
                    <choice><sic>lunching</sic><corr>lynching</corr></choice> is more generallly
                    understood. </p>
                <p>The reasons why the whole subject is deeply and seriously involved in error are
                    <choice><sic>abvious.</sic><corr>obvious.</corr></choice> Those who live in the
                    section where nine-tenths of the lynchings occur do not dare to tell the truth,
                    even if they perceived it. When men know that the
                    <choice><sic>deaht-knell</sic><corr>death-knell</corr></choice> of their
                    aspirations and hopes will be sounded as soon as they express views to which the
                    majority in their immediate vicinage are opposed, they either suppress their
                    views or trim them to fit the popular mind. Only martyrs are brave and bold
                    enough to defy the public will, and the manufacture of martyrs in the negro's
                    behalf is not very brisk just now. Those who do not live in the section where
                    most of the lynchings occur borrow their views from their brothers who do, and
                    so the errors are continually repeated and inevitably perpetuated.</p>
                <p>In the discussion of this subject, four mistakes are commonly made.</p>
                <p>In the first place, it is a great mistake to suppose that rape is the real cause
                    of lynching in the South. Beginning with the <ref target="#Ku_Klux_Klan"/> Ku
                    Klux Klan, the negro has been constantly subjected to some form of organised
                    violence ever since he became free. It is easy to prove that rape is simply the
                    pretext and not the cause of lynching. Statistics show that, out of every
                    hundred negroes who are lynched, from seventy-five to eight-five are not even
                    accused of this crime, and many who are accused of it are innocent. And, yet,
                    men who admit the accuracy of these figures gravely tell the county that
                    lynching can never be suppressed, until negroes cease to commit a crime with
                    which less than one-fourth of those murdered by mobs are charged.</p>
                <p>The prevailing belief that negroes are not tortured by mobs unless they are
                    charged with the <quote>"usual"</quote> crime, does not tally with the facts.
                    <ref target="#Mississppi_Lynching"/>The savagery which attended the lynching of
                    a man</p>
                <p>
                    <tag type="bottom">(1)</tag>
                </p>
            </div>
            <div>
                <p>
                    <tag type="top">(2)</tag>
                </p>
                <p>and his wife the first week in March, a few years ago, was probably never
                    exceeded in this country or anywhere else in the civilized world. A white
                    planter was murdered at Doddsville, Miss., and a negro was charged with the
                    crime. The negro fled and his wife, who was known to be innocent fled with him
                    to escape the fate which she knew awaited for her if she remained. The two
                    negroes were pursued and captured and the following account of the tragedy by an
                    eye-witness appeared in the "Evening Post," a Democratic daily of Vicksburg,
                    Miss.</p>
                <p>
                    <quote>"When the two negroes were captured, they were tied to treed, and while
                        the funeral pyres were forced to suffer the most fiendish tortures. The
                        blacks were forced to hold out their hands while one finger at a time was
                        choppped off. The fingers were distributed as souvenirs. The ears of the
                        <choice><sic>murders</sic><corr>murderers</corr></choice> were cut off.
                        Holbert was beaten severely, his skull was fractured, and one of his eyes,
                        knocked out whit a stick, hung by a shred from the socket. Neither the man
                        nor woman begged for mercy, nor made a groan or plea. when the executioner
                        came forward to lop off fingers, Holbert extended his hand without being
                        asked. The most excruciating form of punishment consisted in the use of
                        large corkscrew into the flesh of the man and woman, in the arms, legs and
                        body, and then pulled out, the spirals tearing out big pieces of raw,
                        quivering flesh every time it was withdrawn. Even this devilish torture did
                        not make the poor brutes cry out. When finally they were thrown on the fire
                        and allowed to be burned to death, this came as a relief to the maimed and
                        suffering victims."</quote>
                </p>
                <p>The North frequently
                    <choice><sic>sumpathizes</sic><corr>sympathizes</corr></choice> with the
                    Southern mob, because it has been led to believe the negro's diabolical assaults
                    upon white women as the chief cause of lynching. In spite of the facts,
                    distinguished representatives from the South are still insisting, in Congress
                    and elsewhere, that <quote>"whenever negroes, cease committing the crime of
                    rape, the lynchings and burnings will cease with it."</quote> But since
                    three-fourths of the negroes who have met a violent death at the hands of
                    Southern mobs have not been accused of this crime, it is evident that, instead
                    of being the <quote>"usual"</quote> crime, rape is the most unusual of all the
                    crimes for which negroes are shot, hanged, and burned.</p>
                <p>Although Southern men of prominence still instist that <quote>"this crime is more
                    responsible for mob violence than all other
                    <choice><sic>crimed</sic><corr>crimes></corr></choice>combined,"</quote> it is
                    gratifying to observe that a few of them, at least are geginning to feel ashamed
                    to pervert the facts. During the past few years, several Southern gentlemen, of
                    unquestioned ability and integrity, have publicly exposed the falsity of this
                    plea. Two years ago, in a masterful article on the race problem, Professor
                    Andrew Sledd, at that time an instructor in a Southern College, Emory College,
                    Georgia, admitted that only a small
                    <choice><sic>numder</sic><corr>number</corr></choice> of the negroes who are
                    lynched are accused of assaulting white women. Said he:</p>
                <p>
                    <quote>"On the contrary, a frank consideration of all the facts, with no other
                        desire than to find the truth, the whole truth, and nothing but the truth,
                        however contrary to our wishes and</quote>
                </p>
            </div>
            <div>
                <pb n="3" facs="Terrell_Image3.jpg"/>
                <p>
                    <tag type="top">(3)</tag>
                </p>
                <p>
                    <quote>humiliating to our section the truth may be, will show that by far the
                        most of our Southern lynchings are carried through in <hi rend="underlined"
                        >sheer, unqualified and increasing brutality</hi>."</quote>
                </p>
                <p>But a heavy penalty was paid by this man who dared to make such a frank and
                    fearless statement of facts. He was forced to resign his position as professor,
                    and lost prestige in his section in various ways. In the summer, some years ago,
                    Bishop Candler of Georgia made a strong protest against lynching, and called
                    attention to the fact that, out of 128 negroes who had been done to death during
                    one certain year, only 16 were even accused of rape.</p>
                <p>In the second place, it is a mistake to suppose that the negro's desire for
                    social equality sustains any relation whatsoever to the crime of rape. According
                    to the testimony of eye-witnesses, as well as the reports of Southern
                    newspapers, the negroes who are know to have been guilty of assault have, as a
                    rule, been ignorant, repulsvie in appearance and as near the brute creation as
                    it is possible for a human being to be. It is safe to assert that, among the
                    negroes who have been guilty of ravishing white women, not one has been taught
                    that he was the equal of white people or had ever heard of social equality. And
                    if by chance he had heard of it, he had no clearer conception of its meaning
                    than he had of the principle of the binomial theorem. In conversing with a large
                    number of ignorant negroes, the writer has never found one who seemed to have
                    any idea of what social equality means, or who expressed a desire to put this
                    theory into practice when it was explained to him.</p>
                <p>Negroes who have been educated in Northern institutions of learning with white
                    men and women, and who for that reason might have learned the meaning of social
                    equality and have acquired a taste for the same, neither assault white women nor
                    commit other crimes, as a rule. A careful review of the facts will show that
                    negroes who have the "convention habit" developed to a high degree, or who are
                    able to earn their living by editing newspapers, do not belong to the criminal
                    class, <choice><sic>alghouth</sic><corr>although</corr></choice> such negroes
                    are always held up by Southern gentlemen as objects of ridicule, contempt and
                    scorn. Strange as it may appear, illiterate negroes, who are the only ones
                    contibuting largely to the educated, cultivated members of the race, they are
                    held up as bright and shining examples of what a really good negro should be.
                    The dictionary is searched in vain by Southern gentlemen and gentlewomen for
                    words sufficiently ornate and strong to express their admiration for a dear old
                    "mammy" or a faithful old "uncle," who can neither read nor write, and who
                    assure their white friends they would not, if they could.</p>
                <p>On the other hand, no language is sufficiently caustic, bitter and severe, to
                    express the disgust, hatred and scorn which Southern gentlement feel for what is
                    called the "New Issue," which, being interpreted, means, negroes who aspire to
                    knowledge and culture, and who have acquired a taste for the highest and best
                    things in life. At the door of this "New Issue," the sins and shortcomings of
                    the hole race are laid. This "New Issue" is beyond hope of redemption, we are
                    told, because somebody, nobody knows who, has taught it to believe in social
                    equality, something, nobody knows what. The alleged fear of social equality has
                    always been used by the South to explain its unchristian treatment of the negro
                    and to excuse its many crimes. How many crimes have been committed, and how many
                    falsehoods have been </p>
            </div>
            <div>
                <p>
                    <tag type="top">(4)</tag>
                </p>
                <p>uttered, in the name of social equality by the South. Of all these, the greatest
                    is the determination to lay lynching at its door. In the North, which is the
                    only section that accords the negro the scrap of social equality enjoyed by him
                    in the United States, he is rarely accused of rape. The only form of social
                    equality ever attempted between the two races, and practiced to any considerable
                    extent, is that which was originated by the white masters of slave women, and
                    which has been perpetuated by them and their descendants even unto the present
                    day. Of whatever other crime we may accuse the big, black burly brute, who is so
                    familiar a figure in the reports of rape and lynching-bees sent out by the
                    Southern press, surely we cannot truthfully charge him with an attempt to
                    introduce social equality into this republican form of government, or to foist
                    it upon a democratic land. There is no more connection between social equality
                    and slavery before the war, or any other form of oppression to which the negro
                    has uniformly been subjected in the South.</p>
                <p>The third error on the subject of lynching consists of the widely circulated
                    statement that the moral sensibilities of the best negroes in the United States
                    are so stunted and dull, and the standard of morality among even the leaders of
                    the race is so low that they do not appreciate the enormity and heinousness of
                    rape. <choice><sic>Thos</sic><corr>Those</corr></choice> who claim to know the
                    negro best and to be his best friends delare, that he usually
                    <choice><sic>sumpathizes</sic><corr>sympathizes</corr></choice> with the black
                    victim of mob violence rather than with the the white victim of the black
                    fiend's lust, even when he does not go so far as to condone the crime of rape.
                    Only those who are densely ignorant of the standards and sentiments of the best
                    negroes, or who wish wilfully to misrepresent and maliciously to slander a race
                    already resting under burdens greater than it can bear, would accuse its
                    thousands of reputable men and women of sympathizing with rapist, either black
                    or white, or of condoning their crime. The negro preachers and teachers who have
                    had the advantage of education and moral training, together with others
                    occupying the positions of honor and trust, are continually expressing their
                    horror of this one particular crime, and exhorting all whom they can reach by
                    voice or pen to do everything in their poser to wash the ugly stain of rape from
                    the race's good name. And whenever the slightest pity for the victim of mob
                    violence is expressed by a negro who represents the intelligence and decency of
                    his race, it is invariably because there is a reasonable doubt of his innocence,
                    rater then because there is condonation of the alleged crime.</p>
                <p>Everbody who is well informed on the subject of lynching knows that many a negro
                    who has been accused of assault or murder, or other violation of the law, and
                    has been tortured to death by a mob, has afterward been proved innocent of the
                    crime with which he was charged. So great is the thirst for the negro's blood in
                    the South, that but a single breath of suspicion is sufficient to kindle into an
                    all-consuming flame the embers of hatred ever smouldering in the breasts of the
                    fiends who compose a typical mob. When once such a bloodthirsty company starts
                    on a negro's trail, and the right one cannot be found, the first available
                    specimen in sacrificed to their rage, no matter whether he is guilty or not.</p>
                <p>A white man who died near Charleston, South Carolina, in March,</p>
            </div>
            <div>
                <pb n="4" facs="Terrell_Image4.jpg"/>
                <p>
                    <tag type="top">(5)</tag>
                </p>
                <p>some few years ago, confessed on his death-bed that he had murdered his wife,
                    although three negroes were lynced for this crime at Ravenel, South Carolina, in
                    May, two years previously. This murder was one of the most brutal ever committed
                    in the State, and the horrible tortures of which the three innocent negroes were
                    subjected indicated plainy that the mob intended the punismhment to fit the
                    crime. <ref target="#Carrollton_Miss_Lynching"> At one time, three negroes, a
                    mother, her daughter and her son, were lynched in Carrollton, Miss., because it
                    was rumored that they had heard of a murder before it was committed, and had not
                    reported it.</ref> <ref target="#Shreveport_LA_Lynching">A negro was accused of
                    murdering a woman, and was lynched in Shreveport, Louisiana, on another
                    occcasion, who was afterward proved innocent.</ref> The woman who was lynched in
                    Mississippi shortly after, was not even accused of a crime. The charge of murder
                    had not been proved against her husband, and, as the white man who was murdered
                    had engaged in an altercation with him, it is quite likely, if the negro had
                    been tried in a court of law, it would have been shown to be a case of
                    justifiable homicide. And so other cases might easily be cited to porve that the
                    charge that innocent negroes are sometimes lynched is by no means without
                    foundation. It is not strange, therefore, that even reputable, law-abiding
                    negroes should protest against the tortures and cruelties inflicted by mobs
                    which wreak vengeance upon the guilty and innocent and upon the just and unjust
                    of their race alike. It is to the credit and not to the shame of the negro that
                    he tries to uphold the sacred majesty of the law, which is so trailed in the
                    dust and trampled under foor by white mobs.</p>
                <p>In the fourth place, it is well to remember, in discussing the subject of
                    lynching, that it is not always possible to ascertain the facts from the
                    accounts in the newspapers. The facts are often suppressed, intentionally or
                    unintentionally, or distorted by the press. The case of Sam Hose, to which
                    reference has so often been made, is a good illustration of the unreliability of
                    the press in reporting the lynching of negroes. Sam Hose, a negro, murdered
                    Alfred Cranford, a white man, in a dispute over wages which the white employer
                    refused to pay the colored workman. It was decided to make an example of a negro
                    who dared to kill a white man. A well-known, influential newspaper immediately
                    offered a reward of $500. for the capture of <ref target="#Sam_Hose_Lynching"
                    >Sam Hose.</ref> This same newspaper predicted a lynching and stated that,
                    though several modes of punishment had been suggested, it was the consensus of
                    opinion that the negro should be burned at the stake and tortured before being
                    burned. A rumor was started, and circulated far and
                    <choice><sic>wife</sic><corr>wide</corr></choice> by the press, that Sam Hose
                    had assaulted the wife of Alfred Cranford, after the latter had been killed. One
                    of the best detectives in Chicago was sent to Atlanta to investigate the affair.
                    After securing all the information it was possible to obtain from black and
                    white alike, and carefully weighing the evi dence, this white detective declared
                    it would have been a physical impossibility for the negro to assault the
                    murdered man's wife, and expressed it as his opinion that the charge of assault
                    was an invention intended to make the burning a certainty</p>
                <p>The Sunday on which Sam Hose was burned was converted into a holiday. Special
                    trains were made up to take the Christian people of Atlanta to the scene of the
                    burning, a short distance from the city. After the first train moved out with
                    every inch of available </p>
            </div>
            <div>
                <p>
                    <tag type="top">(6)</tag>
                </p>
                <p>space inside and out filled to overflowing, a second had to be made up, so as to
                    accommodate those who had just come from church. After Sam Hose had been
                    tortured and burned to death, the great concourse of Christians who had
                    witnessed the tragedy scraped for hours among his ashes in the hope of finding a
                    sufficient number of his bones to take to their friends as souvenirs. The charge
                    has been made that Sam Hose boasted to another negro that he intended to assault
                    Alfred Cranford's wife. It would be difficult for anybody who understands
                    conditions in the South to believe that a sane negro would announce his purpose
                    to violate a white woman there, then
                    <choice><sic>deliverately</sic><corr>deliberately</corr></choice> enter her
                    husband's house, while all the family were present, to carry out his threat. </p>
                <p> <choice><sic>To</sic><corr>Two</corr></choice> years ago a riot occurred in
                    Atlanta, Georgia, in which four white policemen were killed and several wounded
                    by a colored man named Richardson, who was himself finally burned to death.
                    Through the press the public was informed that the negro was a desperado. As a
                    matter of fact, Richardson was a merchant, well to do and law-abiding. The head
                    and front of his offending was that he dared to reprimand an ex-policeman for
                    living in open adultery with a colored woman. When it was learned that this
                    negro had been so impudent to a white man, the sheriff led out a posse,
                    consisting of the city police, to arrest Richardson. Seeing the large number of
                    officers surrounding his house, and knowing what would be his fate, if caught,
                    the negro determined to sell his life dear, and he did. With the exception of
                    the Macon "Telegraph," but few white newspapers ever gave the real cause of the
                    riot, and so Richardson has gone down to history as a black desperado, who shot
                    to death four officers of the law and wounded as many more. Several years ago,
                    near New Orleans, a negro was at work in a corn-field. In working through the
                    corn he made considerable noise, which frightened a young white woman, who
                    happened to be passing by. She ran to the nearest house, and reported that a
                    negro had jumped at her. A large crowd of white men immediately shouldered guns
                    and seized the negro, who had no idea what it meant. When told why he was taken,
                    the negro protested that he had not even seen the girl whom he was accused of
                    frightening, but his protest was of no avail and he was hanged to the nearest
                    tree. The press in formed the country that this negro was lynched for attempted
                    rape. Instance after instance might be cited to prove that facts bearing upon
                    lynching, as well as upon other phases of the race problem, are often garbled---
                    without intention, perhaps --- by the press.</p>
                <p>What, then, is the cause of lynching? At the last analysis, it will be discovered
                    that there are just two causes of lynching. In the first place, it is due to
                    race hatred, the hatred of a stronger people toward a weaker who were once held
                    as slaves. In the second place, it is due to the lawlessness so prevalent in the
                    section where nine-tenths of the lynchings occur. View the question of lynching
                    from any point of view one may, and it is evident that it is just as impossible
                    for the negroes of this country to prevent mob violence by any attitude of mind
                    which they may assume, or any course of conduct which they may pursue, as it is
                    for a straw dam to stop Niagara's flow. Upon the same spirit of intolerance and
                    of hatred the crime of lynching must be fastened as that which called into being
                    the Ku-Klux Klan, and which has prompted more recent exhibitions of hostility
                    toward the negro, such as the
                    <choice><sic>disgranchisement</sic><corr>disfranchisement</corr></choice> acts,
                    the <ref target="#Jim_Crow_Laws"/>Jim Crow Car Laws, and the new slavery called
                    <ref target="#Peonage"/> "peonage,"</p>
            </div>
            <div>
                <pb n="5" facs="Terrell_Image5.jpg"/>
                <p>
                    <tag type="top">(7)</tag>
                </p>
                <p>together with other acts of oppression which make the negro's lot so hard.</p>
                <p>Lynching is the aftermath of slavery. The white men who shoot negroes to death
                    and flay them alive, and the white women who apply flaming torches to their
                    oil-soaked bodies to-day, are the sons and daughters of women who had but
                    little, if any, compassion on the race when it was enslaved. The men who lynch
                    negroes to-day are, as a rule, the children of women who sat by their firesides
                    happy and proud in the possession
                    <choice><sic>andand</sic><corr>and</corr></choice> affection of their own
                    children, while they looked with unpitying eye and adamantine heart upon the
                    anguish of slave mothers whose children had been sold away, when not overtaken
                    by a sadder fate. If it be contended, as it often is, that negroes are rarely
                    lynched by the descendants of former slaveholders, it will be difficult to prove
                    the point. According to the reports of lynchings sent out by the Southern press
                    itself, mobs are generally composed of the "best citizens" of a place, who
                    quietly disperse to their homes as soon as they are certain that the negro is
                    good and dead. The newspaper who predicted that Sam Hose would be lynched, which
                    offered a reward for his capture and which suggested burning at the stake, was
                    neither owned nor edited by the poor whites. But if it be conceded that the
                    descendants of slave holders do not shoot and burn negroes, lynching must still
                    be regarded as the legitimate offspring of slavery. If the children of the poor
                    whites of the South are the chief aggressors in the lynching-bees of that
                    section, it is because their ancestors were brutalized by their slaveholding
                    environment. In discussing the lynching of negroes at the present time, the
                    heredity and the environment, past and present, of the white mobs are not taken
                    sufficiently into account. It is as impossible to comprehend the cause of the
                    ferocity and barbarity which attend the average lynching bee without taking into
                    account the brutalizing effect of slavery upon the people of the section where
                    most of the lynchings occur, as it is to investigate the essence and nature of
                    fire without considering the gases which cause the flame to ignite. It is too
                    much to expect, perhaps, that the children of women who for generations looked
                    upon the hardships and the degradation of their sisters of a darker hue with few
                    if any protests, should have mercy and compassion upon the children of that
                    oppressed race now. But what a tremendous influence for law and order, and what
                    a mighty foe to mob violence Southern white women might be, if they would arise
                    in the purity and power of their woman hood to implore their fathers, husbands
                    and sons no longer to stain their hands with the black man's blood!</p>
                <p>While the men of the South were off fighting to keep the negro in bondage, their
                    mothers, wives and daughters were entrusted to the black man's care. How
                    faithfully and loyally he kept his sacred trust the records of history attest!
                    Not a white woman was violated throughout the entire war. Can the white women of
                    the South forget how black men bore themselves throughout that
                    <choice><sic>tryint</sic><corr>trying</corr></choice> time? Surely it is not too
                    much to ask that the daughters of mothers who were shielded from harm by the
                    black man's constancy and care should requite their former protectors, by at
                    least asking that, when the children of the latter are accused of crime, they
                    should be treated like human beings and not like wild animals to be butchered
                    and shot.</p>
                <p>If there were one particularly heinous crime for which an in furiated people took
                    vengeance upon the negro, or if there were a genuine</p>
            </div>

            <div>
                <p>
                    <tag type="top">(8)</tag>
                </p>
                <p>fear that a guilty negro might escape the penalty of the law in the South, then
                    it might be possible to explain the cause of lynching on some other hypothesis
                    than that of race hatred. It has already been shown that the first supposition
                    has no foundation in fact. It is easy to prove that the second is false. Even
                    those who condone lynching do not pretend to fear the delay or the uncertainty
                    of the law, when a guilty negro is concerned. With the courts of law entirely in
                    the hands of the white man, with judge and jury belonging to the superior race,
                    a guilty negro could no more extricate himself from the meshes of the law in the
                    South than he could slide from the devil-fish's embrace or slip from the
                    anaconda's coils. Miscarriage of justice in the South is possible only when
                    white men transgress the law.</p>
                <p> In addition to lynching, the South is continually furnishing proof of its
                    determination to wreak terrible vengeance upon the negro. The recent shocking
                    revelations of the extent to which the actual enslavement of negroes has been
                    carried under the peonage system of Alabama and Mississippi, and the unspeakable
                    cruelties to which men, women and children are alike subjected, all bear witness
                    to this fact. In January of the present year, a government detective found six
                    negro children ranging in age from six to sixteen years working on a Georgia
                    plantation in bare feet, scantily clad in rags, although the ground was covered
                    with snow. The owner of the plantation is one of the wealthiest men in northeast
                    Georgia, and is said to have made his fortune by holding negroes in slavery.
                    When he was tried it was shown that the white planter had killed the father of
                    the six children a few years before, but was acquitted of the murder, as almost
                    in variably happens, when a white man takes a negro's life. After the death of
                    their father, the children were treated with incredible cruelty. They were often
                    chained in a room without fire and were beaten until the blood streamed from
                    their backs, when they were unable to do their stint of work. The planter was
                    placed under $5,000 bail, but it is doubtful whether he will ever pay the
                    penalty of his crime. Like the children just mentioned hundreds of negroes are
                    to-day groaning under a bondage more crushing and more cruel than that abolished
                    forty years ago.</p>
                <p>This same spirit manifests itself in a variety of ways. Efforts are constantly
                    making to curtail the <ref target="#Segregation_in_Schools"/> educational
                    opportunities of colored children. Already one State has enacted a law by which
                    colored children in the public schools are prohibited from receiving instruction
                    higher than the sixth grade, and other States will, doubtless, soon follow this
                    lead. It is a well-known fact that a Governor recently elected in one of the
                    Southern States owes his popularity and his votes to his open and avowed
                    opposition to the education of negroes. Instance after instance might be cited
                    to prove that the hostility toward the negro in the South is bitter and
                    pronounced, and that lynching is but a manifestation of this spirit of vengeance
                    and intolerance in its ugliest and most brutal form. </p>
                <p>To the widespread lawlessness among the white people of the South lynching is
                    also due. In commenting upon the blood guiltiness of South Carolina, the
                    Nashville "American" declared some time ago that, if the killings in the other
                    States had been in the same ratio to population as in South Carolina, a larger
                    number of people would have been murdered in the United States during 1902 than
                    fell on the</p>
            </div>


            <div>
                <pb n="6" facs="Terrell_Image6.jpg"/>
                <p>
                    <tag type="top">(9)</tag>
                </p>
                <p>American side in the Spanish and Philippine wars.</p>
                <p>Whenever Southern white people discuss lynching, they are prone to slander the
                    whole negro race. Not long ago, a Southern writer of great repute declared
                    without qualification or reservation that "the crime of rape is well-nigh wholly
                    confined to the negro race," and insisted that "negroes furnish most of the
                    ravishers." These assertions are as unjust to the negro as they are unfounded in
                    fact. According to statistics recently published, only one colored male in
                    100,000 over five years of age was accused of assault upon a white woman in the
                    South in 1902, whereas one male out of every 20,000 over five years of age was
                    charged with rape in Chicago during the same year. If these figures prove
                    anything at all, they show that the men and boys in Chicago are many times more
                    addicted to rape than are the negroes in the South. </p>
                <p>A few years ago, two white men were arrested in the national capital for
                    attempted assault upon little children. One was convicted and sentenced to six
                    years in the penitentiary. The crime of which the other was accused was of the
                    most infamous character. A short account of the trial of the convicted man
                    appeared in the Washington dailies, as any other criminal suit would have been
                    reported; but if a colored man had committed the same crime, the newspapers from
                    one end of the United States to the other would have published it broadcast.
                    Editorials upon the total depravity and the hope less immorality of the negro
                    would have been written, based upon this particular case as a text. With such
                    facts to prove the falsity of the charge that " the crime of rape is well-nigh
                    wholly confined to the negro race," it is amazing that any writer of repute
                    should affix his signature to such a slander.</p>
                <p>But even if the negro's morals were as loose and as lax as some claim them to be,
                    and if his belief in the virtue of women were as slight as we are told, the
                    South has nobody to blame but itself. The only object lesson in virtue and
                    morality which the negro received for 250 years came through the medium of
                    slavery, and that peculiar institution was not calculated to set his standards
                    of correct living very high. Men do not gather grapes of thorns nor figs of
                    thistles. Throughout their entire period of bondage colored women were debauched
                    by their masters. From the day they were liberated to the present time,
                    prepossessing young colored girls have been considered the rightful prey of
                    white gentlemen in the South, and they have been protected neither by public
                    sentiment nor by law. In the South, the negro's home is not considered sacred by
                    the superior race. White men are neither punished for invading it, nor lynched
                    for violating colored women and girls. In discussing this phase of the race
                    problem last year, one of the most godly and eloquent ministers in the Methodist
                    Episcopal Church (white) expressed himself as follows: </p>
                <p> <quote>"The negro's teachers have been white. It is from the white man the negro
                    has learned to lie and steal. If you wish to know who taught the negro
                    licentiousness, you have only to look into the faces of
                    <choice><sic>thousnads</sic><corr>thousands</corr></choice> of mulatto people
                    and get your answer." </quote>When one thinks </p>
            </div>


            <div>
                <p>
                    <tag type="top">(10)</tag>
                </p>
                <p>how the negro was degraded in slavery, which discouraged, when it did not
                    positively forbid, marriage between slaves, and considers the bad example set
                    them by white masters, upon whom the negroes looked as scarcely lower than the
                    angels, the freedman's self-control seems almost like a miracle of modern times.
                    In demanding so much of the negro, the South places itself in the anomalous
                    position of insisting that the conduct of the inferior race shall be better, and
                    its standards higher, than those of the people who claim to be superior. </p>
                <p>The recent lynching in Springfield, Ohio, and in other cities of the North, show
                    how rapidly this lawlessness is spreading throughout the United States. If the
                    number of Americans who participate in this wild and diabolical carnival of
                    blood does not diminish, nothing can prevent this country from becoming a by
                    word and a reproach throughout the civilized world. When Secretary Hay appealed
                    to Roumania in behalf of the Jews, there were many sarcastic comments made by
                    the press of that country and of other foreign lands about the inhuman treatment
                    of the negro in the United States. In November, 1903, a manifesto signed by
                    delegates from all over the world was issued at Brussels, Belgium, by the
                    International Socialist Bureau, protesting against the lynching of negroes in
                    the United States.</p>
                <p> It is a source of deep regret and sorrow to many good Christians in this country
                    that the church puts forth so few and such feeble protests against lynching. As
                    the attitude of many minis ters on the question of slavery greatly discouraged
                    the abolition ists before the war, so silence in the pulpit concerning the lynch
                    ing of negroes to-day plunges many of the persecuted race into deep gloom and
                    dark despair. Thousands of dollars are raised by our churches every year to send
                    missionaries to Christianize the heathen in foreign lands, and this is proper
                    and right. But in addition to this foreign missionary work, would it not be well
                    for our churches to inaugurate a crusade against the barbarism at home, which
                    converts hundreds of white women and children into savages every year, while it
                    crushes the spirit, blights the hearth and breaks the heart of hundreds of
                    defenceless blacks? Not only do ministers fail, as a rule, to protest strongly
                    against the hanging and burning of negroes, but some actually condone the crime
                    without incurring the displeasure of their congrega tions or invoking the
                    censure of the church. Although the church court which tried the preacher in
                    Wilmington, Delaware, accused of inciting his community to riot and lynching by
                    means of an incendiary sermon, found him guilty of "unministerial and
                    unchristian conduct," of advocating mob murder and of thereby breaking down the
                    public respect for the law yet it simply admonished him to be "more careful in
                    the future" and inflicted no punishment at all. Such indifference to lynching on
                    the part of the church recalls the experience of Abraham Lincoln, who refused to
                    join church in Springfield, Illinois, because only three out of twenty-two
                    ministers in the whole city stood with him in his effort to free the slave. But,
                    however unfortunate may have been the attitude of some of the churches on the
                    question of slavery before the war, from the moment the shackles fell from the
                    black man's limbs to the present day, the American Church has been most kind and
                    generous in its treatment of the backward and struggling race</p>
            </div>



            <div>
                <pb n="7" facs="Terrell_Image7.jpg"/>
                <p>
                    <tag type="top">(11)</tag>
                </p>
                <p>Nothing but ignorance or malice could prompt one to disparage the efforts put
                    forth by the churches 'in the negro's behalf. But, in the face of so much
                    lawlessness to day, surely there is a r?le for the Church Militant to play. When
                    one reflects upon the large number of negroes who are yearly hurled into
                    eternity, unshriven by priest and untried by law,, one cannot help realizing
                    that as a nation we have fallen upon grave times, indeed. Surely, it is time for
                    the ministers in their pulpits and the Christians in their pews to fall upon
                    their knees and pray for deliverance from this rising tide of bar barism which
                    threatens to deluge the whole land</p>
                <p>How can lynching be extirpated in the United States? There are just two ways in
                    which this can be accomplished. In the first place, lynching can never be
                    suppressed in the South, until the masses of ignorant white people in that
                    section are educated and lifted to a higher moral plane. It is difficult for one
                    who has not seen these people to comprehend the density of their igno rance and
                    the depth of their degradation. A well-known white author who lives in the South
                    describes them as follows: </p>
                <p>
                    <quote>"Wholly ignorant, absolutely without culture, apparently without even the
                        capacity to appreciate the nicer feelings or higher sense, yet conceited on
                        account of their white skin which they constantly dishonor, they make, when
                        aroused, as wild and brutal a mob as ever disgraced the face of the
                        earth."</quote>
                </p>
                <p>In lamenting the mental backwardness of the white people of the South, the
                    Atlanta "Constitution" expressed itself as follows two years ago : "We have as
                    many illiterate white men over the age of twenty-one years in the South to-day
                    as there were fifty-two years ago, when the census of 1850 was taken." Over
                    against these statistics stands the record of the negro, who has reduced his
                    illiteracy 44.5 per cent, in forty years. The hostility which has always existed
                    between the poor whites and the negroes of the South has been greatly
                    intensified in these latter days, by the material and intellectual advancement
                    of the negro. The wrath of a Spanish bull, before whose maddened eyes a red flag
                    is flaunted, is but a feeble attempt at temper compared with the seething,
                    boiling rage of the average white man in the South who beholds a well-educated
                    negro dressed in fine or becoming clothes. In the second place, lynching cannot
                    be suppressed in the South until all classes of white people who dwell there,
                    those of high as well as middle and low degree, respect the rights of other
                    human beings, no matter what may be the color of their skin, become merciful and
                    just enough to cease their persecution of a weaker race and learn a holy
                    reverence for the law.</p>
                <p> It is not because the American people are cruel, as a whole, or indifferent on
                    general principles to the suffering of the wronged or oppressed, that outrages
                    against the negro are per mitted to occur and go unpunished, but because many
                    are igno rant of the extent to which they are carried, while others despair of
                    eradicating them. The South has</p>
            </div>


            <div>
                <p>
                    <tag type="top">(12)</tag>
                </p>
                <p>carried, while others despair of eradicating them. The South has so
                    industriously, persistently and eloquently preached the inferiority of the
                    negro, that the North has apparently been converted to this view the thousands
                    of negroes of sterling qualities, moral worth and lofty patriotism to the
                    contrary notwithstanding. The South has insisted so con tinuously and
                    belligerently that it is the negro's best friend, that it understands him better
                    than other people on the face of the earth and that it will brook interference
                    from nobody in its method of dealing with him, that the North has been persuaded
                    or intimidated into bowing to this decree.</p>
                <p>Then, too, there seems to be a decline of the great convictions in which this
                    government was conceived and into which it was born. Until there is a
                    renaissance of popular belief in the prin ciples of liberty and equality upon
                    which this government was founded, lynching, the Convict Lease System, the
                    Disfranchise ment Acts, the Jim Crow Car Laws, unjust discriminations in the
                    professions and trades and similar atrocities will continue to dishearten and
                    degrade the negro, and stain the fair name of the United States. For there can
                    be no doubt that the greatest obstacle in the way of extirpating lynching is the
                    general attitude of the public mind toward this unspeakable crime. The whole
                    country seems tired of hearing about the black man's woes. The wrongs of the
                    Irish, of the Armenians, of the Roumanian and Russian Jews, of the exiles of
                    Russia and of every other oppressed people upon the face of the globe, can
                    arouse the sympathy and fire the indignation of the American public, while they
                    seem to be all but indifferent to the murderous assaults upon the negroes in the
                    South. </p>
            </div>
            <div>
                <p>
                    <tag type="centered">(Watermark) Mary Church Terrell.</tag>
                </p>
                <p>
                    <tag type="centered">-------0-------</tag>
                </p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
    <standOff>
        <listEvent>
            <event xml:id="Arkansas_Lynching">
                <label>Arkansas County Lynching:</label>
                <desc> 15 people were murdered by a white mob. One of the deadliest lynchings in
                    American history. The murderers were never identified. Began on March 21st, when
                    a white man argued over a gambling game with a black man. A fight ensued. The
                    headline states only eleven victims with two more killed later.</desc>

            </event>
            <event xml:id="Mississppi_Lynching">
                <label>Luther Holbert Lynching:</label>
                <desc> Luther Holbert and a woman, perhaps his wife, were tortured and killed in
                    Doddsville, Mississippi. Mr. Holbert was accused of murdering a white landowner,
                    James Eastland. Eastland's two brothers captured Holbert and the unknown woman. </desc>

            </event>
            <event xml:id="Carrollton_Miss_Lynching">
                <label>Carrollton Lynching:</label>
                <desc> Mother, son, and daughter are lynched in Carrollton, Mississippi. Mob
                    composed of 500 men and women took these individuals out of the jail and took
                    them to be hanged. Judge pleads for the mob to not take the law into their own
                    hands, but to no effect. </desc>
            </event>
            <event xml:id="Shreveport_LA_Lynching">
                <label>Shreveport Lynching:</label>
                <desc> A woman is lynched in Shreveport, Lousiana. Jennie Steers, who allegedly
                    poisoned Elizabeth Dolan was lynched on the Beard plantation. Steers was also
                    accused of the murder of Mrs. Frank Mathews, her employer. This was the first
                    woman lynched in Louisiana. </desc>
            </event>
            <event xml:id="Sam_Hose_Lynching">
                <label>Sam Hose Lynching:</label>
                <desc> Sam Hose in 1899, was accused of murdering his employer, Alfred Cranford.
                    Cranford threatened Hose with a revolver and in self-defense, Hose killed him.
                    Hose fled the scene. Cash rewards from the governor and from the newspaper
                    "Atlanta Constitution," were offered for his capture. A mob had found him in
                    Newnan, Georgia. They brutally tortured and burned him to death. </desc>
            </event>
            <event xml:id="Jim_Crow_Laws">
                <label>Jim Crow Laws:</label>
                <desc> These laws were meant to marginalize African Americans begining with Black
                    codes starting right after the Civil War. These laws put Black citizens back
                    into indentured servitude through peonage, took away voting rights, and
                    controlled where they lived. These laws were expanded to segregate public parks,
                    theaters, restaurants, restrooms, water fountains, elevators, and
                    cemeteries.These laws did not go away until the Civil Rights Movement and even
                    still today, there are remenants of these laws that still lurk around.</desc>
            </event>
            <event xml:id="Segregation_in_Schools">
                <label>Segregation in Schools:</label>
                <desc> Upheld by the court case Plessy v. Ferguson, segregation in schools was legal
                    as long as it was equal. That was never the case, though, as many black schools
                    had low funds, causing lower test scores. Aside from grades, the general
                    attitude was that black students weren't worth anything and even the kids
                    realized that. Despite being finally repealed in the court case Brown v. Board
                    of Education, many schools are still segregated based on the geographical
                    neighborhoods, leading to similar consequences. </desc>
            </event>
            <event xml:id="Ku_Klux_Klan">
                <label>Ku Klux Klan:</label>
                <desc> This organization began in 1865 in Pulaski, Tennessee. It started as a
                    private club for Confederate veterans but soon turned into a secret society that
                    preyed on and terrorized Black communities. They would lynch individuals,
                    vandalize and destroy homes, schools, and businesses of black citizen and their
                    members consisted of people from all classes, from high levels of government
                    down to low-class people in poverty.</desc>
            </event>
            <event xml:id="Peonage">
                <label>Peonage:</label>
                <desc>A system where a worker must pay off a debt with work. This system was in
                    place, despite being illegal in 1867, until the 1940s. In many cases, the worker
                    would never be able to pay off their debt and would continue to work without
                    being paid, essentially, a slave. </desc>
            </event>
        </listEvent>
        <listBibl>
            <bibl>
                <pb facs="StCharles.jpg"/>
            </bibl>
            <bibl>
                <pb facs="Mississippi_Newspaper.jpg"/>
            </bibl>
            <bibl>
                <pb facs="Mississippi_Newspaper2.jpg"/>
            </bibl>
            <bibl>
                <pb facs="Woman1.jpg"/>
            </bibl>
            <bibl>
                <pb facs="Woman2.jpg"/>
            </bibl>
            <bibl>
                <pb facs="Woman3.jpg"/>
            </bibl>
            <bibl>
                <pb facs="Woman4.jpg"/>
            </bibl>
            <bibl>
                <pb facs="Woman5.jpg"/>
            </bibl>
            <bibl>
                <pb facs="Woman6.jpg"/>
            </bibl>
            <bibl>
                <pb facs="Woman7.jpg"/>
            </bibl>
            <bibl>
                <pb facs="Louisiana1.jpg"/>
            </bibl>
            <bibl>
                <pb facs="Sam_Hose1.png"/>
            </bibl>
            <bibl>
                <pb facs="Sam_Hose2.png"/>
            </bibl>
        </listBibl>
        <listAnnotation>
            <note>
                <name>History.com Editors</name>
                <date>March 26, 2021</date>
                <title>Jim Crow Laws</title>
                <abbr>https://www.history.com/topics/early-20th-century-us/jim-crow-laws</abbr>
            </note>
            <note>
                <name>PBS</name>
                <title>Slavery v. Peonage</title>
                <abbr>https://www.pbs.org/tpt/slavery-by-another-name/themes/peonage/</abbr>
            </note>
            <note>
                <name>Jerry Rosiek</name>
                <date>January 21, 2019</date>
                <title>School Segregation: A realist's view</title>
                <abbr>https://kappanonline.org/school-segregation-realists-view-rosiek/</abbr>
            </note>
            <note>
                <name>Arkansas Gazette</name>
                <date>March 26th, 1904</date>
                <title>Eleven Negroes Victim of Mob</title>
                <abbr>http://encyclopediaofarkansas.net/media/st-charles-lynching-article-11830/</abbr>
            </note>
            <note>
                <name>Los Angeles Herold</name>
                <date>February 8th, 1904</date>
                <title>Burned at the stake by Mississippi mob</title>
                <abbr>cdnc.ucer.edu</abbr>
            </note>
            <note>
                <name>San Francisco Call</name>
                <date>August 2nd, 1901</date>
                <title>Negro Women and Children are Lynched</title>
                <abbr>cdnc.ucer.edu</abbr>
            </note>
            <note>
                <name>Urbana Daily Courier</name>
                <date>July 28th, 1903</date>
                <title>A woman is lynched</title>
                <abbr>idnc.library.illinois.edu</abbr>
            </note>
            <note>
                <name>Atlanta Constitution</name>
                <date>April 27th, 1899</date>
                <title>Burned to Death</title>
                <abbr>http://tps.ghslearn.com/newspaper-article-on-the-sam-hose-lynching/</abbr>
            </note>
        </listAnnotation>
    </standOff>
</TEI>
